SpaceX is currently preparing for what's
expected to be the largest IPO in
history with a target valuation as high
as 1.75 trillion dollars. To put that in
perspective, that's larger than Meta or
Tesla and it would comfortably unseat
Saudi Aramco for the title of the
biggest stock market debut of all time.
The offering is expected to see massive
demand from retail investors who have up
until now been unable to invest as the
company's private. Now, in the aerospace
world, there's a very important
distinction between astronomy and
astrology. Astronomy is the branch of
science that uses math to calculate
orbital mechanics, so your multi-billion
dollar rocket doesn't turn into a very
expensive firework. Astrology, on the
other hand, is the belief that you
should stay home from work next week
because Jupiter's feeling a bit spicy.
Usually, the people building rockets and
the people casting horoscopes don't have
very much in common. Elon Musk obviously
cares about astronomy, the science. He
has, after all, spent decades talking
about the importance of going to Mars
and building rockets. We know that he
also loves a bit of numerology, too. No
one finds the numbers 420 and 69 funnier
than Elon Musk does. With the IPO
announcement, we've learned that he
loves a bit of astrology, too. As SpaceX
has reportedly set its sights on IPO-ing
this June because Jupiter, Venus, and
Mercury will be forming a rare
conjunction in the sky and I suppose
that's auspicious. On top of that, June
also happens to be the month of Musk's
55th birthday and to top it all off,
there are rumors that the date being
targeted is June the 9th. Yep, that's
right, June the 9th or 69. If Musk was a
bit younger, it would be on 67, but he's
not. He's he's a 55-year-old man, so uh
69 it is.
Well, the planetary alignment makes for
a great headline. The timing is possibly
driven by a much more terrestrial
concern, the race for limited capital.
As of early 2026, the private markets
are starting to look tapped out. Venture
capital funds that have spent the last
few years aggressively funding the AI
doom are now facing a liquidity plateau
and are under pressure to finally return
some cash to their own investors. At the
same time, Musk is in a high-stakes race
to reach the public markets before his
rivals, OpenAI and Anthropic, soak up
all of the available demand. Bankers are
quietly warning that there might not be
enough spare change in the public
markets to support three massive
capital-intensive AI listings at the
same time. And the first mover might get
the biggest slice of the pie. With xAI
burning through a billion dollars a
month and massive data center projects
requiring billions more in
infrastructure, Musk may not be just
watching the stars, he might be watching
the exits, too. The planetary alignment
might be a nice bit of branding, but
it's possibly the fear of being second
in line at the ATM that's really fueling
the countdown. This rush to the public
markets represents a significant change
of heart for Musk. For over a decade,
he's insisted that SpaceX would not go
public until his Mars transport system
was fully in place. He argued that the
short-term pressures of being a public
company, where investors obsess over
quarterly performance and short-sellers
hit you with large stakes, would be a
distraction from the long-term goal of
making life multiplanetary.
But, as we head towards the June 2026
listing, the Mars transport system is
still very much a work in progress, and
Musk has recently started sweeping those
red planet ambitions under the rug like
an embarrassing teenage phase. The new
mission, and the core of the IPO pitch,
is focused on the moon, a destination
that Musk once dismissed as a waste of
time. He now describes the moon as a
stepping stone and the overriding
priority for securing the future of
civilization. It turns out that this
shift of focus is a lot easier when
you've been foreshadowing it for years,
even if accidentally. Elon Musk has been
wearing his famous Occupy Mars t-shirts
since 2019, which a number of people
have pointed out actually features a
red-tinted picture of the moon during a
lunar eclipse. It's possible that he
hasn't abandoned his Mars mission. Maybe
he just took a close look at his own
chest and realized that he's been
accidentally advertising for the moon
all along. But, before we dig into the
financial black hole of space-based data
centers, let me tell you about this
week's video sponsor, Saylite, an eSIM
provider who makes it incredibly easy to
travel and stay connected without having
to pay ridiculous foreign roaming
charges, find a local SIM card, or ruin
your trip searching around for public
Wi-Fi networks that you can use. I tried
Saylite out last summer, and I found it
really convenient. It's an app that you
install on your phone, which allows you
to stay connected in over 200 places
around the world. There's no need to buy
and swap SIM cards like I used to do.
Instead, you just download the app and
use it whenever you're traveling. You
just select the country and plan you
want, and activate an eSIM before you
leave home. When you land, your phone
automatically connects to a local
network with no hidden charges. It's
much cheaper than roaming and takes just
seconds to get going. There's no fussing
around at the airport. You can book an
Uber, access GPS, or make a call. If
you're traveling soon, get an exclusive
15% discount on Saily data plans.
Download the Saily app and use the code
boil at checkout.
The transition from a high-flying
rocketry and satellite firm into what we
might now call the XXX conglomerate,
SpaceX, xAI, and X, has been described
by supporters as an act of genius and by
critics as a massive bailout. This is
because just as the SpaceX IPO was being
finalized, Musk decided to fold xAI into
SpaceX at a $250 billion price tag.
Merging a rocket company with an AI
startup is strange enough, but xAI comes
with some particularly heavy social
media baggage. Last year, xAI, the AI
company, used its shares to buy Elon
Musk's everything app, X, the platform
formerly, and in truth still, known as
Twitter. This means SpaceX investors are
now, by extension, the proud owners of
the number 17-ranked social media
website. A business that's been
struggling with a persistent exodus of
both users and advertisers since Musk
bought it for $44 billion
in 2022.
To justify the $250 billion price tag,
you have to believe that xAI is a
top-tier player in AI. Currently,
ChatGPT and Google's Gemini dominate the
field, holding over 85% of the market
between them. Grok, by comparison, sits
at a distant 3.4% market share. One
problem is that Grok is effectively an
island. While XAI recently launched a
standalone Grok app, the vast majority
of its usage remains trapped inside
Twitter. Most of Grok's use is just
fact-checking tweets or generating the
kind of unfiltered memes that have
landed the company in regulatory hot
water in Spain, France, and the UK.
While SpaceX is said to be profitable,
generating about $8 billion in EBITDA
last year, XAI is a money furnace,
burning through a billion dollars in
cash every single month. In a world
where AI could be a winner-take-all
market, much like internet search was,
being a lower-ranked player like XAI is
possibly a dangerous place to be. That
danger is exacerbated by a growing
talent drain. Since the start of the
year, a significant number of key staff
have left XAI, including six of the
original founders who were poached from
Google and DeepMind. It's hard to
justify a frontier AI premium when the
very people who have built the model
have left the building. Musk's
explanation for the merger, delivered in
a press release that reads like the
script of a low-budget sci-fi epic, is
that we need to build orbital data
centers to extend the light of
consciousness to the stars. He argues
that space-based AI is the only way to
scale because space is called space for
a reason.
It's a move that mirrors the Solar City
merger from 2016, where Musk used
Tesla's balance sheet to bail out a
struggling solar company he also
happened to own. As Bloomberg's Matt
Levine pointed out, the innovation
engine here isn't just about rockets,
it's about a fundraising ability that
allows Musk to negotiate with himself
and set his own valuations without the
nuisance of independent board oversight.
Amusingly, right before I filmed this
video, Elon Musk tweeted that xAI was
not built right the first time around,
so it's being rebuilt from the
foundations up, which might lead SpaceX
investors to ask if this was the case,
why did they just pay $250 billion for
it? For the banks and venture capital
firms who were stuck in the underwater
Twitter deal, the merger is fantastic
news. It effectively swaps their
struggling social media equity for shiny
new SpaceX stock right before a massive
IPO. And while SpaceX investors might be
wondering why they're suddenly
subsidizing an anime girlfriend chatbot,
most are unlikely to complain. In the
world of investing alongside Elon Musk,
loyalty is the primary currency. If you
complain too loudly about the corporate
governance, you risk being cut out of
the next auspicious planetary alignment.
To justify merging a rocket company with
a money furnace chatbot, the IPO
narrative relies on a very specific
vision of the future based around the
importance of moving the world's AI
computing power off planet. Musk's
argument is that terrestrial data
centers are hitting a wall because of
land, power, and cooling constraints.
His solution is to launch a
constellation of a million satellites to
act as orbital data centers, directly
harnessing near constant solar power in
the vacuum of space.
At first glance, the pitch might seem to
have a certain logic. It's always sunny
in space and there are no neighbors to
complain about the noise. But in
practice, the engineering hurdles are
huge. Take cooling, for example. On
Earth, we keep servers from overheating
by blowing cold air or water over them,
a process called convection. In the
vacuum of space, there's no air to move
heat away. The only option is to use
massive radiators that eject heat as
infrared radiation.
We've already seen a test of this
concept. A startup launched an AI
satellite a few months ago that was
about the size of a small refrigerator
carrying an Nvidia H100 chip. While the
chip was able to successfully train a
tiny AI model on the works of
Shakespeare, it couldn't run around the
clock because it had to shut down
frequently when it got too hot to
function. The company's next version is
scheduled to launch later this year and
they say that it will carry the second
largest cooling radiator array in space.
The only larger one being the cooling
array on the International Space
Station. So, to run just a handful of AI
chips in orbit, you need hardware that
rivals the most expensive structure ever
built by humanity, the International
Space Station, and then you have to
scale that up to the 1 million
satellites mentioned in the SpaceX press
release. To reach the gigawatt scale
capacity Musk is talking about, you
would need solar arrays and radiators
measuring roughly 4 km in length.
Getting something that size, roughly the
size of 40 football fields, into orbit
and maintaining it would be a logistical
nightmare. It would be a giant fragile
sail vulnerable to every piece of space
debris in low Earth orbit.
Then there's the issue of Starship. The
entire Sentient Sun business model
relies on SpaceX reaching an insane
flight rate. We're talking about
launches every hour carrying 200 tons
per flight, according to SpaceX's own
press release.
Currently, Starship is still in the
frequent explosion phase of development.
While the engineering team has achieved
the incredible feat of catching a 70-m
booster with giant robot arms, the
rocket is yet to perform a full orbital
mission or prove that it can reliably
deploy payloads without what SpaceX
calls a rapid unscheduled disassembly.
To round out the sci-fi sales pitch,
Musk has even proposed building
factories on the moon. I'm not making
this up. According to the press release,
the plan is to manufacture satellites
taking advantage of lunar resources and
then fire them into deep space using an
electromagnetic mass driver, basically a
giant space railgun, a technology that
the US Navy spent over $500 million
on over a 16-year period with no
success. Apparently, the railgun
prototypes suffered from extreme heat
and physical stresses, the types of
problems which would be only more of an
issue in space. It's not clear to me why
a factory on the moon would be more
efficient than a factory in even the
most remote places on Earth or what moon
resources Musk is planning on taking
advantage of. I would imagine some sort
of supply chain still needs to be
developed there.
It is a bold vision and it represents a
massive U-turn for a man who spent
decades calling lunar missions a
distraction from going to Mars. If you
remember, in 2017, he claimed that he
would be sending at least two cargo
missions to Mars in 2022 to find water
sources and establish power, mining, and
life support infrastructure so that the
first crude missions could follow in
2024.
He later reaffirmed this target in 2018
and again in 2020 before the timeline
was delayed. Ultimately, building a data
center in a desert or specialized
warehouse on Earth will always be
cheaper and easier than trying to build
them in space or manufacture and launch
them from the moon. Andrew Mcallup, an
engineer who works for a space startup,
has built a web-based calculator that
allows the cost of an orbital data
center to be compared with the cost of
an equivalent terrestrial one. It
estimates that building a 1 GW data
center and running it for 5 years on
Earth costs around $16 billion
excluding chips, and an orbital
equivalent would cost over $50 billion,
so more than three times as much. The
thing is, that building a few data
centers in Texas won't justify a $1.75
trillion valuation. For that, you need a
sentient sun and a moon catapult. Now,
this is possibly a recurring theme for
Elon Musk. The idea that the hardest way
of doing something is actually the most
efficient. This is, after all, the same
man who once claimed that digging miles
of tunnels underground would somehow be
orders of magnitude cheaper and faster
than just building a road on the
surface. Apparently, if you can convince
investors that the laws of physics and
basic accounting are just optional
suggestions, you can put almost any
price tag on the results. If you can
ignore the sentient suns and the lunar
catapults for a moment, you're still
left with the daunting task of
justifying a $1.75 trillion sticker
price for SpaceX. To be clear, that
doesn't mean that Elon Musk won't get
that price, it just means that it would
be extremely difficult to explain.
Based on what's being reported, this
isn't just a regular IPO, it's a
carefully managed liquidity event for a
company that's simply outgrown its
capacity to source new funding in the
private markets. For more than 20 years,
SpaceX has existed in a private market
bubble where valuations are set by small
isolated capital raises rather than the
cold reality of daily public trading.
But, as former head of equity capital
markets from Bank of America, Craig
Coben points out in the Financial Times,
the laws of financial gravity are a lot
harder to bend than space-time.
The primary metric for any high-growth
tech company is the enterprise value to
sales ratio. It's particularly favored
for rapidly growing firms that are
either not yet profitable or have
inconsistent earnings. This is because
sales figures are often more stable and
less susceptible to accounting
distortions than net income or EBITDA.
The ratio tells you how much are you
paying for every dollar of revenue the
company brings in. Facebook, Coben
points out, went public at 11 times
forward sales. This was considered
extremely expensive at the time, and it
pushed the boundaries of what public
markets were willing to tolerate. To add
more context, most high-growth tech
companies back then were trading at much
lower multiples. Google, for instance,
was trading around five to six times
sales. SpaceX is looking to list at
roughly 94 times its 2025 revenue. Even
if we use the most optimistic
projections for 2026, the ratio still
sits at over 60 times sales. For
context, that's significantly higher
than Palantir, which currently has the
highest multiple in the S&P 500.
Not everyone thinks that that price is
crazy, however. The analysts at
PitchBook recently made the case that a
$1.75 trillion valuation is expensive
but justifiable if you assume that
Starlink will reach 1.2 billion users by
2040.
The deep flaw in that math is a concept
called the total addressable market.
Based on Hans Rosling's research in the
book Factfulness, there are only about 1
billion people on the planet who earn
more than $32 a day. Most of those
people live in the United States and
Western Europe. And most people in those
parts of the world already have access
to wired broadband, which is both faster
and cheaper than Starlink. A total
addressable market of 1.2 billion users
being able to spend over $100 a month
solely on internet connectivity is next
to impossible. Starlink is a brilliant
tool for people in remote areas, gold
miners in Sudan, or the military in
Ukraine, but it's ill-suited for cities
where the dish needs a clear view of the
sky and because satellites suffer from
network congestion when too many people
connect to the same one all at once.
Realistically, there are only about 32
million households in the world who can
afford the service and don't already
have wired internet access. Most of that
group already have access to the
internet using mobile phone networks,
and less than half of them might feel
that cellular speed and connectivity is
not good enough and are willing to pay
up for Starlink access. Expecting
Starlink to jump from its current 10
million subscribers to 1.2 billion is
like expecting everyone on the planet to
start drinking Fiji bottled water even
when they already have access to clean
drinking water. We're already seeing the
limits of this growth in the financial
data. Elizabeth Lopatto at The Verge
recently pointed out that a 2024 Morgan
Stanley report projected that Starlink
revenue would reach $19 billion the next
year on the strength of 6 million
subscribers. SpaceX then managed to
reach 9.2 million subscribers that year,
more than 50% better than expected, but
its revenue was only $16 billion.
This implies that as Starlink grows its
customer base, its margins are falling.
Let's talk about the company's
questionable profitability next. SpaceX
recently touted $8 billion in EBITDA,
but as a number of analysts have noted,
EBITDA, earnings before interest, taxes,
depreciation, and amortization, is a
very generous lens through which to view
a company like SpaceX, which has very
high research and development costs and
very high depreciation. EBITDA is often
used to help investors compare very
similar businesses that have made
different investment and accounting
decisions over time, but companies that
essentially run the same business, and
you're just stripping out leverage
choices, the jurisdictions they're taxed
in, and their accounting choices over
the timelines they've chosen to spread
out their costs. This can make sense.
It's a great way to make a clean
comparison of the cash flow generation
power and business operations of two
very similar widget manufacturing
companies. In the case of high capex
businesses with enormous cash burn on
early-stage research and development
operations, EBITDA becomes very
questionable. SpaceX satellites have a
useful life of around 5 years. This
means that when you capitalize the build
costs of these satellites and send them
up to space as investments on your
balance sheet initially, you later incur
depreciation expenses, where you spread
out the cost of those satellite bills
over their 5-year useful lifespans.
Excluding significant expenses like this
that are core to the business's ongoing
operations and capacity to generate
future cash flow is particularly
distorted for a business like SpaceX.
They simply couldn't continue to run
their proposed operations without
continuing to replace these satellites.
Excluding the cost of the satellites and
the cost of getting them into lower
Earth orbit to claim profitability is
somewhat ridiculous. If you then account
for the billions in cash used to build
Starship in terms of research and
development, the thing Musk is alluding
to as profit starts to look quite
difficult to ever capture. Very large
research and development spend to go to
Mars or to go to the moon can only be
recouped with high-volume future
deployments or high payload usage of the
tools that they design and build. In
practice, the launch market of
delivering cargo into space has
exhibited very little growth outside of
SpaceX delivering its own Starlink
satellites into space, leading to the
question of whether this is a growth
business at all. When you move away from
EBITDA and start analyzing the actual
profitability, the picture is not nearly
as pretty. It's essentially the picture
of Dorian Gray of financial statements.
The IPO pitch looks young and flawless,
but the balance sheet in the attic is
looking increasingly narled. While
SpaceX is a $16 billion revenue
business, leaked documents show that xAI
generated just $120 million in revenue
during the first 9 months of 2025. To
put that in perspective, xAI is
currently burning through $1 billion a
month to build its data centers. That
means that xAI spends its entire annual
revenue every 6 days. By merging the two
businesses, Musk is using the moat of
the rocket business to subsidize the
astronomical cost of the AI business,
all while asking the public to pay a
massive premium for the privilege of
owning shares. Ultimately, SpaceX might
be an extraordinary engineering success,
but as a public investment, the price
you pay for the expected growth will
matter. If the valuation is based on
comic book heroic assumptions about
capturing a billion customers that
either already have better internet
access or can't afford to pay for the
service, the final frontier for
investors might be a very long way down.
This all leads us to the question of how
Elon Musk actually expects to get that
$1.75 trillion price tag. The answer
isn't found in the physics of rockets,
but instead in the physics of the stock
market. The most important thing to
understand about this IPO is that SpaceX
isn't selling the whole company to the
public. They're likely only releasing a
tiny float. The financial press is
suggesting that just 5 to 10% of the
total shares might be issued. By keeping
the supply of stock artificially low
while marketing it to every retail
investor on the planet, this could
create a supply squeeze before the
opening bell even rings. When everyone
wants a piece of the future, but there
are only a few shares to go around, the
price has only one way to go, and that's
up. Craig Colburn wrote about this low
float strategy a few years ago in the
Financial Times, where he pointed out
that a lot of recent tech IPOs had
floated only a tiny number of shares,
often between 7%
compared to the historical average of
20%. He used the example of Instacart
where only 8% of the shares were floated
and of those 60% went to cornerstone
investors and 5% to friends and family.
This left a tiny supply of shares to be
traded, presumably to cultivate a sense
of scarcity. The real magic for SpaceX
might happen with the index inclusion
trap. This isn't just a lucky break for
Elon Musk, it's reported to be driven by
a specific demand from him. According to
Reuters, SpaceX made early inclusion in
the Nasdaq 100 index a necessary
condition for agreeing to list on the
exchange. In response, the exchange is
consulting on a new rule that would
allow SpaceX to join the Nasdaq 100
after just 15 trading days, bypassing
the year of price discovery required for
every other company. And it isn't just
the Nasdaq, either. Bloomberg reports
that S&P Dow Jones Indices is also
considering historic rule changes to
fast-track SpaceX into the S&P 500. This
is significant because there are roughly
$24 trillion
tied to that index. Maybe Elon can get
on the phone to the people at Russell to
see if he can get SpaceX classified as a
value stock, too. If SpaceX is added to
the S&P 500 and the Nasdaq 100, every
passive investor will find themselves
buying the stock at whatever price the
supply squeeze is manufactured. As
veteran fund manager George Noble points
out, the proposed five-times float
multiplier used to determine its Nasdaq
index weighting is shameless structural
manipulation. It effectively turns every
pension fund into exit liquidity for
SpaceX insiders, where your retirement
account is being forced to buy into a
bubble designed by the seller. As Noble
argues, the rules are being rewritten to
benefit IPO issuers and early-stage
insiders, and your capital is the tool
being used to enrich them.
We've seen this movie before. In
December 2020, Tesla was added to the
S&P 500 after a massive run-up in price.
Since the day of inclusion, Tesla has
underperformed the broader index by more
than 20%. The passive investors who were
forced to buy in at a huge valuation
right before sales started drying up
became the bag holders, while the early
insiders took their victory laps.
>> [snorts]
>> SpaceX may be an extraordinary
engineering company, but it's been sold
to the public as a financial miracle at
a price that is, to me, very difficult
to explain. That doesn't mean that the
IPO will fail or the stock price will
fall, but a lot of things will have to
go right for SpaceX for it to be a good
long-term investment. If you found this
video interesting, you should watch my
video on MicroStrategy's infinite money
glitch failing next. Don't forget to
check out our sponsor Salely using the
link in the video description, and see
you in the next video. Bye.
>> [music]